Welcome back to another
video with It's Dr.
Dan and today we're going
to be looking at ions.
So what are ions all about?
We're going to be looking at
something called cations and anions.
Now where do these come from?
Well, if you remember from learning
about the periodic table, one thing about
is that atoms are inherently neutral,
meaning naturally they're found with
an equal number of protons and anions.
Well, if you remember from learning
about the periodic table, one
thing about is that and anions.
Well, if you remember and electrons.
However, some of them have the tendency
to either gain or lose electrons, in order
to try to fulfill its octet rule, or maybe
its duet rule for something like hydrogen.
So one thing that we're going to be
learning about is looking at cations.
So to remember this, this terminology,
cations, or if you think of a cat, it
has paws, and they are positive, right?
So they're pawsitive.
Anions or I think of
onions, they're negative.
They kind of make you cry a little
bit when you smell them, right?
So you have cat ions and anions.
So ions in general as
a blanket term, right?
Is any type of charge particle.
And this is from the gain
or the loss of electrons.
So we're gonna be looking at both of these
two different, uh, types of ions here.
to try to get an understanding of what
they hold and how we can count our
protons and electrons in this video.
All right, let's go take a look at them.
Cations are going to be the first
ion that we are going to examine.
So what is a cation?
Well, cations are positive, meaning
that they have a positive charge.
So certain elements will, or
certain atoms will have a tendency
to want to lose an electron.
In order to help it be at a lower
energy state, to be more relaxed.
So, if I have, let's say, lithium here,
what I am showing is that we have,
lithium is losing one of its electrons,
so notice how they are separated.
And it's all written on the other side
of this arrow here, so it's letting you
know it's yielding, it's breaking apart.
So, when we are writing a charge, we are
going to write this as a superscript.
This is very similar to the idea of
an exponent, so if you reviewed your
mathematics, right, you have exponents.
We will just put a plus or a minus, in
this case a plus, to show you the charge.
This can be written as plus one,
which is just a plus like so.
Um, this is the same thing as
saying, or I have one plus like this.
It can be written as two plus,
three plus, four plus, and so forth.
And it's all depending on the number
of electrons that have been lost.
So if I lost, let's say, two electrons,
you would see this written as two plus.
If I lost three electrons, you would see
three plus written down in the statement.
So lithium though, it only loses one.
So what exactly, how does, what
does this exactly represent?
How, why a plus, why are we doing that?
Well, the way to kind of imagine this
is think of it in terms of scales.
So when we are losing electrons,
we are becoming more positive.
So if you go to your, if
you have your periodic table
handy and if not, that's okay.
But trying to think about it, lithium,
what atomic number does it have?
Well, lithium has a, essentially
a 3 as its atomic charge,
or sorry, atomic number.
So that means it has 3 protons
because it has an atomic number of 3.
Now, naturally, being that
they are inherently neutral, it
will also have three electrons.
Now, when this thing breaks down and
loses an electron, well, that number
is going to change as a result.
We will have, still
have our three protons.
The number of protons never
changes for any of the ions.
the number of protons is what
identifies these species.
So lithium is lithium
because of the three protons.
So that does not ever change.
Only the electrons, I can't say that
enough, only the electrons change.
Um, so once we lose that electron,
notice how now there's only two
electrons and the other electron left.
The atom, and then it probably went to
go bond, maybe go to another atom that
needed it or something to create a bond.
That's for another day, another lecture.
So, when that happens, notice how we
have more positives, so think of scales.
The positive side is going to be heavier
weighted as a result, and it falls down.
Meaning it is overall more positive.
So that's where this plus charge
comes from, because we have 3 verse 2.
So that's why we show
this as lithium plus.
So, member cations are more positive,
they are losing electrons, and
they become positive as a result.
You would think when you see the
plus, that means that It gained
electrons, but it's the opposite.
It's all about scales.
Think of the charge balance.
So when we are trying to solve
for ion charge, we can do simple
calculations to check for ourselves.
So the way that we can get that plus
one, it's a very simple calculation.
We just take the number of protons.
We subtract it from the number
of electrons, so 3 minus 2.
What do you get?
You would get a plus 1 as your charge.
So this is where that math is coming from.
It's protons minus electrons.
And you can do this for any species.
It's something that's a good one
to have in the back of your, like
your back of your notebook somewhere
and have it like boxed off to know
how to calculate ionic charge.
Let's look at Anions are the same
general idea, but it's going to be
the opposite case, being that onions
think of how they make you cry, right?
Meaning that we're going to be, um,
in this case, gaining electrons are
becoming more negative as a result.
So in this case, you can see that
I have a neutral fluorine over here
and it is gaining one electron.
Okay.
So we're gaining, therefore it's
making a ion or an anion in this
case, notice how it is more negative.
So how exactly does this work?
Well, if you think of fluorine, and
we were to count all the little orbs
it has, so we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 9, that means it has 9 protons.
And as it's neutral, it has 9 electrons.
So if it gains one more electron,
what's going to happen, the scales are
going to be distorted and the electrons
are going to be more as a result.
So we'll still have nine protons,
but now we're going to have a
total of ten electrons because
we gained that one extra.
So when we do that little simple math,
we can see, okay, if we have nine protons
minus those ten electrons, and we have
a negative one charge as a result.
So this is what an anion is all about.
When you gain an electron, you become
more negative, and it shows that, okay,
you have more electrons than protons.
Remember, every proton has a plus one
charge, every electron has a negative
one charge, so we can see what is that.
Let's take a look at some
examples practicing counting
our protons and electrons.
So for, for our example for this
video, we're going to be counting how
many protons and electrons there are.
This is what can allow you to actually
be able to predict the charges, how to
write them, when you are to see them.
Um, so for example, if I were
to ask you how many protons,
how many electrons, We're for
potassium with a plus one charge.
How exactly would you do that?
Well, first thing you have to
identify is what does the plus mean?
And if you can remember from before
as a positive means that there's
less electrons as our cat ion, right?
It's positive.
It has pause.
So what you're going to have to do
is go to a periodic table and find
potassium, and what we can see is, okay,
potassium is right over here, and it
has a number of 19 as its atomic number.
So what we'll do is we'll write that down.
So we have 19 protons.
So you just write a 19 with a p, and
then that plus, that tells you protons.
And being that we have one
less electron, we will write 18
electrons to count that, okay?
Because it's not neutral anymore,
so they're not going to be equal.
Now what if I wanna do strontium?
Okay, so ssr.
So once again, we have to find Sr
on the pract table and you can see
it's right in your potassium, but
it's on a different column here.
So we have Sr and we're gonna
do the same general idea.
It has an atomic number of 38,
so our protons are equal to 38.
Therefore, how many electrons do we have?
In this case we have a two plus.
So we, that means we
have two less electrons.
So it's going to be a total of
36 electrons, and that is where
that 2 plus charge comes from.
Now with nitrogen, same idea,
we go to our periodic table,
we look what our number is.
When we go through this, we're going to
see that we have a total of 7 protons,
because it has an atomic number of 7.
And then when you look up, so thinking,
okay, I have a 3, and it's negative,
so that means I have more electrons.
So we can write down that we have 10
electrons for this particular ion.
Well, in our last one, which is bromine,
so bromine, as we kind of, and I'll
circle nitrogen as we went, because I
didn't go down to the periodic table.
Bromine is down over here, it's number 35,
so that means it has 35 protons, and being
that it's negative, it's more negative,
so that means if we think of the scales,
right, the 36 is a little bit lower, so
that means it has 36 electrons when we
think of the balance between the two.
Now, how do you know where the ions are?
The good news is many of the ions
are considered to be predictable.
So let's take a look at that.
What exactly does that mean?
The good news is many of the ions that you
will come across in general chemistry or
introductory chemistry are predictable.
Meaning that there is a trend that
essentially hidden in the periodic
table, but it's not very hard to find.
Um, it has to actually
do with the columns.
So on the left hand side of the periodic
table and the right hand side, the left
is mainly as all your metals, the right
is all non metals, meaning they have a
tendency to what they actually want to do.
Metals typically are willing to give
up an electron, meaning they want to
usually be a cation, in 99 percent
of cases in general chemistry.
Nonmetals tend to want to take an
electron, and it all has to do with
their octet rule and trying to get
to 8 electrons, which is the primary
objective for all these different
species when they're bonding, which
we'll talk about in other videos.
So, the easy way to remember,
see this is, okay, over here,
so I have my first columns.
The first column, number one, the way
to remember that is this is going to
essentially, the whole column has a
tendency to have a plus one charge.
And one thing you're going to notice
is, It actually has to do with their
valence electrons and how many they have.
So one thing on their outermost
layer, lithium, for example,
has one valence electron.
So it's willing to lose that one electron.
Same with sodium and potassium.
So all of them, that whole
column, is going to be a plus one.
Okay, so being that that's blue,
we can kind of try to highlight the
entire column as going to be plus one.
Now, when it comes to the next one, which
is plus 2, the next column, well, it's
going to be the same general idea, right?
This whole entire column is going to have
a tendency to be plus 2, and that goes
all the way down to the bottom, too, even
though I kind of stopped the highlighting.
It's the whole column.
Alright, so that means every single
element in that column has a tendency to
want to lose two electrons in this case.
So we have plus one, plus two,
and it goes off your columns.
Now, I wish that trend always continued.
It's not always as simple,
um, but we can kind of go over
to the other side over here.
Now, the noble gases, which is
helium, neon, argon, krypton, these
electrons are completely happy.
They have all their electrons
in their outermost layer.
They do not want to lose.
They don't want to gain.
They do not react.
They don't do anything.
The way to remember that one is, okay,
these are just going to be a big fat zero.
They're neutral.
They don't want to do anything.
Meaning that the next column, which
is the halogens, so where fluorine is,
and chlorine, and bromine, this is all
going to be negative one in this case.
So, one minus here.
So, this entire column is going to be one.
Minus.
Okay.
So all of that will be our first one.
And we'll put that there.
So as we move over, the next
column will be 2 minus, and the
one next to that will be 3 minus.
So it keeps going, right?
This has a tendency to want to
take more and more electrons.
Because the goal is to try to
take all the electrons that it
can to fill that outermost layer.
So we have 2 minus.
And we have three minus.
Okay, so now we'll highlight this column
in red, and the next column in green.
And the elements that I have
written down are the ones that have
the tendency to do these charges.
So everything below it.
doesn't really have that charge tendency.
It kind of ends at a specific point.
So all these columns have this charge.
Now, is that the only ones
that have this charge?
There are some other spots too.
Um, the first one is what I
refer to as the steps over here.
So the steps start at aluminum
over here on the corner.
So we have aluminum, then we have
zinc, and then we have Silver.
The way to remember these is if you
think of one step, two step, three step.
The first step in this case is
going to be silver in this case.
So if we put a plus one charge, zinc will
be the second one, which is plus two.
Aluminum will be the third step.
So usually what I, where I always start
the steps is aluminum being that It's
kind of on that third column there.
So it will help you kind of remember
where the plus three generally starts.
And then you're just walking
down the steps as you go.
So it goes three, two, one.
And now these are all the predictable
charges that are always the same for ions.
They always have this tendency
to lose or gain electrons.
So the right hand side is your anions.
The left hand side is your cations.
So you can kind of see metals
and then your non metals have
these general abilities here.
Now, hopefully this video kind of
helped you be able to understand
and predict these different things.
Um, it'll be able to help you see
exactly what the charges are on them all.
Um, there will be more videos that
come with more ions and different,
different practice problems.
So keep practicing, keep trying
to understand these concepts.
Let me know what you think if, uh, in,
whether it's in class or in the comment
section or whoever's watching the videos.
Thank you so much for watching.
If you can like and comment,
subscribe if you haven't.
I appreciate all the support.
Thank you all.
Have a wonderful day.